今天的《造物小百科》
Today on How It's Made,
卡车，公路巨兽诞生记
trucks, monster lorries come to life.
创口贴，一年产量达40亿片
Plasters, four billion in just a single year.
那得有多少擦伤啊
That's a lot of grazes.
电脑电路板，为玩家、极客，也为所有普通人
Computer circuit boards, for gamers, geeks, and everyone in between.
还有烈酒，从朗姆酒到白兰地，从伏特加到干邑
And spirits, from rum to brandy, vodka to cognac.
不过先来看
But first,
无论你心仪的车有8个、10个， 还是18个轮子
whether your rig of choice rides on 8, 10, or 18 wheels
这些公路巨兽都是货运行业的支柱
these beasts of the road are the backbone of the haulage industry.
穿越国土，驶向欧洲乃至更远
Across our land and into Europe and beyond,
从生菜到电脑，它们无所不运
they carry everything from lettuces to computers.
欢迎见证一辆卡车的诞生
Welcome to the birth of a truck.
制造这些巨型卡车需要极其复杂的工艺流程
Making these massive trucks requires highly complex procedures
因为零件又重又难操作
as the parts are heavy and tricky to handle.
装配始于承重车架的制造
Assembly begins by fabrication of the bearing frame,
将承载驾驶室、发动机和变速箱
the main part on which will rest the truck's cab, the motor, and the transmission.
大梁有 7.5米和13米的规格
Tempered steel beams are assembled in lengths of 7.5 and 13 meters.
底盘就像一套巨大的积木拼装而成
The chassis is constructed like a huge macaroni set.
钢梁被逐一连接，用强力气动工具拧紧
The beams are attached together and tightened with powerful pneumatic tools.
组装完成后，主底盘被送往下一个工区
Once assembled, the main chassis is transported to the next construction area.
现在开始打造卡车的机械部分
Now the mechanics of the truck are created,
包括差速器、车轴和底盘悬挂
with the differential, axle, and rig suspension.
随后装好制动支架
The brake mounts are then put in place.
接着安装轮毂
The wheel hubs are then attached.
传动轴被插入其中
The transmission shaft is inserted,
它将驱动车轮转动
which will power the driving wheels.
组装好沉重的铸铁制动鼓， 完成后轮的安装
They finish the rear wheel assembly by mounting the heavy brake drum, made of cast iron.
为便于安装，所有部件都倒置组装
To help with the mounting, everything is assembled upside down,
由能吊起12吨重物的桥式起重机协助
with an overhead crane capable of lifting a 12,000 kilo load.
将部件翻转正位
They then turn the part right side up.
下一步是发动机的精细组装
Next step is the detailed construction of the engine.
变速箱被螺栓固定在黄色的发动机上
The transmission is bolted onto the motor, seen in yellow.
在底盘前端安装离合器和变速箱
At the front end of the chassis, the clutch and the transmission are installed.
这些卡车有6到10个轮子
These trucks have between six and ten wheels.
每个轮胎加轮毂共重55公斤
Each tire and wheel together weighs 55 kilos.
由于重量太大，车轮需借助升降装置安装
Because of the weight, the wheels are installed with the help of a lift mechanism.
这个螺栓器可同时拧紧所有车轮螺母
This bolt fastener allows tightening of all the wheel nuts at the same time.
机械部分组装完成，接下来是驾驶室
The mechanical build is now complete, and it's onto the cab assembly.
首先进行喷漆
This begins with painting.
驾驶室向前翻转，便于安装各类部件
The cab is flipped forward to help with the installation of various components.
接下来是驾驶室内部
Now for the cab's interior.
首先安装仪表台
They begin by installing the dashboard.
接着连接所有线束、指示灯、车速表和踏板
Following this, they attach all the wires, indicators, speedometer, and the pedals.
随后装好座椅，驾驶室完成后用螺栓固定到底盘上
The seats are then fixed, and with the cab completed, it's bolted onto the chassis.
最后安装引擎盖、车灯、排气管和挡泥板
Lastly, the bonnet, lights, exhaust pipe, and mudguards are fitted.
这辆卡车即将上路
The truck is now almost ready to hit the road.
启动发动机，确认一切运行正常
They start it up and verify that everything is operating properly
然后就可以交付客户了
and now it's ready for delivery to the customer.
组装这样一辆卡车需要100小时工时
It requires 100 hours of work to assemble a truck like this.
尽管自重达5吨
And in spite of their 5,000 kilo weight,
这些卡车最高时速也能轻松达到 120 公里每小时
these trucks can move along at top speeds of 120 kilometers an hour
并能运输重达28吨的货物
and transport loads of up to 28 tons.
它们是公路上真正的劳模
They are the true workhorses of the road.
手指割伤了？
Cut your finger?
可以裹上厚厚的纱布，也可以贴一片创口贴
You can wrap it up in bulky gauze or you can apply a plaster.
既然生活崇尚快速解决，创口贴总能胜出
And since we live in a society of quick fixes, the plaster wins out every time.
下次小家伙擦破膝盖时
So next time the little one grazes their knee,
你就会知道那种叫创口贴的小绷带是怎么做成的
you'll know exactly what goes into making those stitches little bandages called plasters.
创口贴由多种材料制成，其中主要是ETS弹力布
Plasters are made of various materials, but the main one is called ETS,
ETS：单向弹力胶布
这种布只在单一方向有弹性
a fabric which is elastic in only one direction
并形成创口贴的粘合部分
and forms the adhesive part of the bandage.
这卷1800米长的布料能做出180万片创口贴
This 1,800 meter roll of fabric can make 1,800,000 plasters.
在布料的一面涂上薄薄一层胶水
A thin coating of glue is applied to one surface of the fabric
再送入烤箱加热到49摄氏度， 使胶层膨胀产生微孔
then it's heated to 49 degrees centigrade in an oven to puff it up, creating holes.
随后布料重新卷成300米一卷
In the glue coating, then the fabric is newly rolled up into 300 meter lengths.
创口贴有不同尺寸
Bandages are of different sizes.
刀片把涂胶布卷切成不同宽度的条带
These blades cut the glued rolls into strips of varying widths.
这些布卷随后堆放好，准备进入下一步
These rolls are then stacked, ready for the next step,
粘贴那小块柔软的保护垫
application of the little cushioned protective pad.
机器用打磨锋利的刀片切割布垫
A machine cuts the fabric pads with finely honed blades
刀片每6个月打磨一次
that are sharpened every six months.
柔软的布材被分成窄条
The cushioned fabric is separated into narrow strips,
之后将粘到ETS弹力布上
which will later be glued to the ETS fabric.
这些布条已准备好粘贴到创口贴上
The strips are now ready to be applied to the bandages.
创口贴的各部分材料被展开
The bandage components are unrolled.
机器将它们组装、切割并逐一包装
The machine assembles them, then cuts and individually wraps them.
贴上未印刷的白色包装纸, 用来保护创口贴
The unprinted white wrapping paper which protects the plasters. is applied.
接着进入包装环节
And now they proceed to packaging,
每分钟可包装300到1500片创口贴
where between 300 and 1,500 plasters are wrapped per minute.
滚筒打出孔线，让创口贴之间易于分离
This roller perforates holes, which allows the plasters to be easily separated from one another.
小型创口贴的制造方式不同
Small plasters are fabricated differently.
布垫被放置在ETS的中央
The cushioned strip is positioned at the centre of the ETS fabric strip.
布垫此时还未消毒
The cushioned pad isn't yet sterilised.
还要稍等一会
That comes later.
下一步是在创口贴两端
The next step is to apply two plastic paper protectors
贴上两片塑料保护纸，盖住涂胶的两端
over the glue-covered ends of the plaster.
完成后，机械臂用吸力吸起创口贴
Once done, the plaster is drawn by suction with a robotic arm and
放入两层包装纸之间
placed between two wrapping papers.
慢镜头下，包装动作看得更清楚
In slow motion, we see the wrapping action better.
全速运行时，每分钟可包装300片创口贴
At full speed, it can wrap 300 bandages a minute.
创口贴完美包装后从机器中出来
The bandages exit the machine perfectly wrapped.
某些类型的创口贴还需经过
Certain types of plaster have to go through a
连续创口贴机打上透气孔
sequential bandage machine to have aeration holes pierced in them.
这些小孔让空气流通，有助于伤口愈合
These holes allow air to circulate and help promote healing.
创口贴现在准备好了
The plasters are now ready.
有时会在创口贴包装上印刷说明文字
Sometimes instructions are printed onto the plaster wrappers.
两块聚合物印版从一系列滚筒上获取油墨
Two polymer plates receive ink from a series of rollers
以复制出所需图案
in order to reproduce the desired design.
创口贴以极快的速度通过
The plasters pass through at incredibly high speeds.
包装之前，它们最终经过消毒
Before being packaged, they're finally sterilised.
一次消毒1万片
Ten thousand at a time.
创口贴被自动计数并送入滑道
The plasters are automatically counted and placed in a chute
落入包装盒中
and fall into the packaging box.
开头那卷巨大的ETS布料
The large roll of ETS fabric seen at the beginning will
每年可生产近200万片创口贴
have produced nearly two million bandages each year.
这家工厂的年产量高达40亿片
This factory produces a staggering four billion
共65种不同款式
bandages in sixty-five different models.
接下来请看《造物小百科》
Coming up in how it's made
为玩家、极客，也给所有人打造的电脑电路板
Computer circuit boards from gamers, geeks and everyone in between.
未来的电脑，就从这里开始
The computers of the future are here today.
还有烈酒，从朗姆酒到白兰地，从伏特加到干邑，适合各种口味
And spirits, from rum to brandy, vodka to cognac, a tipple for every taste.
广告之后见
See you after the break.
欢迎回到《造物小百科》
Welcome back to how it's made.
稍后我们将看到烈酒，从朗姆酒到白兰地
Later we look at spirits, from rum to brandy,
从伏特加到干邑，适合各种口味和场合
vodka to cognac, a tipple for every taste and occasion.
不过先来看
But first,
短短几年间，电路从一团乱麻的线缆
in just a few years, electronic circuits have shrunk from a tangle of wires
缩小到如今电脑电路板的尺寸
to the size of today's computer circuit board,
而且还在一天天变小
and are getting smaller by the day.
电脑技术的变化速度几乎超过地球上任何其他行业，来跟上脚步
Computer technology changes faster than just about any other industry on Earth, so keep up.
电路板是电脑的一种部件
An electronic circuit board is a computer component
能渲染出惊艳逼真的画面
which can produce stunning and realistic scenes.
这样的3D动画需艺术家和程序员借助图形处理器，耗时4个月才能完成
3D animation like this takes four months of work by artists and programmers with the aid of a graphic processor.
印刷电路板好比一座建筑
A printed circuit board can be compared to a building,
玻纤做的地板，铜线做的走廊
composed of fiberglass floors, copper passageways,
以及连接各层的楼梯构成
and stairs that link the floors between them.
电路板采用两种技术组装
Cards are assembled with two technologies:
表面贴装和直插元件
surface wiring and wiring through the card.
元件放入孔中并焊接固定
The components are placed in the holes and soldered in place.
用钢网将锡膏印刷到电路板上
A stencil is used to apply soldering paste onto the card.
这些锡膏将焊接表面元件
This paste will solder the surface components.
这里把钢网放到印刷机上
Here, they place the stencil onto the printing unit.
锡膏从这些孔漏下
It's through these holes that the soldering paste will run.
机器将锡膏均匀铺开
The machine spreads the soldering paste,
锡膏中含有锡铅合金等成分
which contains, among other elements, a tin lead alloy.
印刷刮刀开始工作
The printing blades go into action.
锡膏穿过钢网孔，覆盖印刷电路板上的金属焊盘
The paste runs through the stencil holes and covers the metallic surfaces of the printed circuit board,
这些位置将承载电流
which will establish the electrical current.
这就是未印刷电路板与印刷电路板的区别
This is the difference between an unprinted card and a printed one.
接下来安装表面贴装元件
Next comes the installation of the surface wiring elements.
由高速贴装机自动定位
They are automatically positioned by this rapid placement machine.
每小时约安装3.6万个元件，相当于每秒10个
About thirty-six thousand components are installed per hour, making ten a second.
这台极其精密的机器配备摄像系统
This incredibly sophisticated machine is equipped with a viewing camera
在安装前检查每个元件的对准和尺寸确保准确无误
which verifies the alignment and dimensions of each part before installation.
另一台不带视觉校验的机器则补装间距小于0.5毫米的贴装点
A less precise machine then fixes parts where the space between two placement points is less than 0.5.
电路板继续送向回流炉
The card continues on its way towards the oven,
在那里完成一道关键工序
which accomplishes an essential operation.
元件固定好后，电路板进入回流焊炉
Once the parts are secured, the card goes into a convection oven,
高温将元件焊接在电路板上
where the heat will solder the parts to the card.
各种电路接口被插入各自对应的孔中
Different circuit connectors are inserted into their respective holes.
这道工序需要灵巧的手法
This operation requires great dexterity.
并由手工完成
and is completed by hand.
金属焊点需要焊接到电路板上
The metallic placement points need to be soldered to the card.
直插元件
The soldering of the circuit components through the card is done
需要在240摄氏度的熔融锡铅合金浴中完成焊接
with a bath of molten tin-lead alloy at a temperature of 240 degrees centigrade.
现在所有元件都已安装，可以进行初次电气测试
Now everything is installed, and an initial electrical test can be carried out.
电路板被放在带电的针床上
The card is placed on a bed of electrified pegs.
这些探针接触电路板的连接点
These pegs make contact with the card's connecting points
从而检测电路板是否存在短路或断路
allowing them to check for short circuits or open circuits in the card.
最后，电脑辅助的功能测试评估电路板的性能
Finally, a computer-aided operating test analyzes the card's performance.
这家公司制造200种不同的电路板
This company fabricates 200 models of different circuit boards
每周产量约4000块
and produces about 4,000 cards each week.
从玩家到极客，再到所有人，欢迎来到未来
From gamers to geeks and everyone in between, welcome to the future.
世界顶级烈酒背后的秘密，归根结底就一个简单配方：
The secrets behind the world's finest alcoholic spirits all boil down to one simple recipe:
把谷物和水混合，然后发酵、蒸馏
mix grain and water, then ferment and distill,
再加上几百年的传统工艺
add a few hundred years of tradition,
你会明白为何酒精至今仍是全世界最受欢迎的杯中物
and you begin to understand why alcohol is still the world's favourite tipple.
蒸馏的原理从古罗马开始就为人所知
The principle of distillation was known to ancient Romans, who mastered the process.
中世纪时，蒸馏器首次从葡萄酒中制出酒精
In the Middle Ages, stills produced the first alcohols from wine.
7世纪，蒸馏工艺得到改进
In the 7th century, the distillation process was improved,
到了15世纪，工艺进一步完善
and by the 15th century, the process was further refined,
才有了今天各种烈酒的生产
leading to the production of today's spirits,
如白兰地、伏特加、朗姆酒、波本和威士忌
such as brandy, vodka, rum, bourbon, and whiskey.
干玉米粒是酿造烈酒的主要谷物
Dried corn kernels is the main grain used in making spirits.
这家酿酒厂每天有几卡车玉米倾卸，共230吨
At this distillery, several truckloads empty out 230 tonnes every day.
玉米粒储存在24米高的储仓中，每座可容纳250吨
The kernels are stored in these 24 metre high silos, which can hold up to 250 tonnes.
这里是酿酒厂的中央控制室
This is the distillery control room,
使用95%玉米酿造出中性酒精，
where they manage a recipe that's 95% corn and produces neutral alcohol
之后再加入其他谷物增添色泽与风味
to which other grains for colour and flavour will be added.
第一步是碾磨谷物
The first step is the milling of the grain.
约8吨玉米粉和1.8万升水
Some 8 tonnes of corn flour and 18,000 litres of water
被送入高压釜中蒸煮90分钟
are introduced into this autoclave and steam cooked for 90 minutes.
酶将淀粉转化为糖
Enzymes transform starch into sugar.
接着加入酵母，酵母把糖转化为酒精
Then they add the yeast, which convert sugar into alcohol.
发酵在38摄氏度下持续60小时
Fermentation lasts 60 hours at 38 degrees centigrade.
我们看到的气泡正是酵母活动产生的
The bubbling we see is created by the action of the yeasts.
发酵开始至今已过去约24小时
Some 24 hours have now passed since the start of fermentation.
这一阶段结束时，玉米油会浮到表面，呈明显的红色
When this stage is ended, corn oil will have come to the surface and is clearly visible by its reddish colour.
发酵后的麦芽浆酒精含量为13%
The fermented mash has a 13% alcohol content.
现在进入下一步——蒸馏
They now move on to the next step, distillation,
蒸馏可让混合液中的蒸汽冷凝
which condenses the vapours of the mix.
在这个三塔蒸馏系统中
It's in this three-column distillation system,
麦芽糖浆在85.5 摄氏度下
at a temperature of 85.5 degrees,
从蒸汽中分离出酒精
that the mash ferments and is distilled by steam to separate the alcohol.
蒸馏期间，用这台旋转滚筒烘干酿酒中使用的谷物
During distillation, they dry the grains used in the recipe in this rotating drum.
烘干后的产物叫酒糟，将用作动物饲料
The resulting product is called draff, and it will be used to make animal feed.
蒸馏至此结束
Distillation is now ended.
为给某些金酒增添香气，他们会加入干柠檬皮、肉桂或香菜籽
To aromatise certain gins, they add dried lemon skins, some cinnamon, or coriander.
朗姆酒和威士忌将装入橡木桶陈酿
Rum and whisky will be aged in oak barrels.
陈酿期间，这些烈酒每年会因蒸发损失约3%的酒精含量
While ageing, these spirits will lose about 3% of their alcohol content annually through evaporation.
同时，酒色会逐渐变深
Also, the colour gradually darkens.
现在可以将酒液从木桶放出装入瓶中
They're now ready to draw out the liquid from the barrels and put it into bottles,
但首先必须检验烈酒的品质
but first they have to verify the quality of the spirits.
将标准产品与新产品进行对比
They compare the standard product with the new production.
这一检验对确保成品质量至关重要
This test is highly important in order to assure the quality of the final product.
灌装开始了
And so bottling begins.
这里每分钟灌装140瓶淡朗姆酒
Here, 140 bottles of light rum are filled every minute.
清洗干净的瓶子在传送带上不断循环
Clean bottles circulate continually on the conveyor,
被送往灌装机
leading them to the filling machine.
封盖机为瓶子盖上瓶盖并将其压紧在瓶口
A capper places caps on the bottles and crimps them onto the necks.
封好并贴标的瓶子随后送往包装车间
The then sealed and labelled bottles head for the packaging department.
另一台机器每分钟灌装120瓶加拿大威士忌
This other machine fills 120 bottles of Canadian whiskey every minute.
这家酿酒厂生产约20种不同的烈酒
In this distillery, some 20 different spirits are produced.
用3.4万吨玉米粒
With 34,000 tons of corn kernels,
每年可生产4400万瓶烈酒
they produce 44 million bottles of spirits every year.
干杯
Cheers.